the holy life yeah so it's the it's the
most fundamental context of the Holy life
fundamental context of the Holy life
it's the uh freedom from suffering
that's as the Buddha said
himself like the sea has only one Taste
of salt so that the dam has only one
Taste of freedom from
suffering um and again you can take that in in a
um and again you can take that in in a
sort of General descriptive manner yes
freedom from suffering but you can also
take that in a manner of quite a quite a
acute form of of of of correct
contemplation like develop the theme of
being free from
suffering contemplate it maintain it um
sort of uh maintain it in your mind have
it endure in your mind don't forget
about it don't lose perspective on
it because if you had Faith uh to begin
with in the Buddhist teaching that offer
you possible way out of suffering that
means you you you will also if you don't
lose perspective had have faith in all
the other instructions he gave the
reasons for celibacy the reasons for
virtue it won't be as hard because you
have faith and you will see it
pertaining to the goal cuz you have that
perspective that's why faith is also uh
could also be enough for somebody to
make effort so you don't necessarily
need to have it all figured out but if
you have faith in the right instruction
and you do it rightly but that doesn't
mean you can sacrifice your perspective
on it so the faith can help you if the
perspective hasn't been compromised if
the purpose hasn't been
obscured why are you doing this why are
you a monk or why are you practicing
dhama to be free from suffering so you
always keep that at the back of your
mind that
purpose and that's how you can get to
get to um differentiate more and more
things that are then compatible with it
and things that are not incompatible and
above all you can that's how you can
also become aware of your own
responsibility for
it like your own habits of craving that
revolve around random things you'll see
wait a minute why am I doing this cuz
now you have perspective this is what's
important to me to be free from
suffering yet here I am like feverishly
engaged with this trying to what's the
purpose of that and I I can't seem to be
able to stop why not cuz you lost
perspective you regain perspective
stopping restraining becomes effortless
or certainly requires less
effort so ging perspective makes things
a lot
easier yes yeah yeah maintain gaining
perspective and maintaining perspective
uh makes things more easier because why
because the
purpose is not obscured or it's
regenerated you know like even as we
mentioned that the other day like even
in the lay world of people are not
necessarily interested in practice
Buddhism like the motivational speakers
and so on talk about finding the purpose
for your life cuz without it
it you're going to be depressed or you
you'll be just wandering aimlessly or
just scratching your cental itch day in
day out nothing but finding a purpose
gives you that meaning which then makes
actions much more easier to do Duty
easier to do restrained enduring things
much easier to do CU you have a greater
purpose so you can make a practice out
of maintaining through contemplation
maintaining in the back of your mind not
actively I want to be free from suffer I
want to be free from suffering just
remind yourself and then let it endure
without forgetting about it not actively
thinking about it but not forgetting
about it either that's the practice of
mindfulness in the nutshell you could
ask yourself from time to time maybe
what is the
point what is the
point of yeah sure yeah you can like
of yeah sure yeah you can like
re-evaluate not in a sense of reevaluate
oh what am I what am I doing but even
that if if necessary sometimes but you
want to be really
just maintaining the direction of your
practice that you already know that's
the whole point so that that's that's a
like a that practice of questioning we
discussed before
um you question yourself as a formal
contemplation not to necessarily find
the right answer but more like to induce
the right attitude they will then bring
that perspective back or clarify it or
introduce New
Perspectives you won't be giving the
right answer CU it's not it's not like a
a quiz question it's more like
Discerning the things that are already
there but you need to see them with the
right type of eyes you need to recognize
them you need to recognize the the
nature of impermanence the nature of non
ownership and so on that's all there
already but not recognizing it means
it's not there for you
CU it's not being
seen so if you have a question like it
doesn't even need to be anything
specific or Technical and just as we
said you remind yourself or you ask
yourself why am I
practicing what's the purpose I've been
doing this Buddhist practice for a
number of years what what's the purpose
of that doesn't matter how far you got
into that practice how how much you know
and you can always re askk yourself that
question and if if you do it rightly you
will just reestablish the perspective or
just remind yourself that that
perspective is still
there either way it's going to result in
mindfulness so if if if if your if your
question is why am I practicing whether
you're a beginner or not a beginner you
ask yourself that and don't jump at the
answer don't rush ah because of this no
just what's the point of this and you'll
see that the answer is already there
otherwise you wouldn't have been doing
it for all these years the point is as
the point always was freedom from
suffering so if you don't feel perhaps
that you're free from suffering enough
then you can press the questions further
again not just so that you can find the
right answer that will please you but
more like that through that attitude of
questioning you will start to look in
the direction uh different from the
already made answer that would come your
way the question that will inevitably
then have to result in in Greater
perspective eventually it might be more
ambiguous perspective and that's why
people fear to
question their own beliefs their own
efforts because by putting it in
question means you're already questioning well
means you're already questioning well
you're already
implying uh that it could have also been
invalid so I must not question it then
that's how I will not think about a
possibility of me being wrong for
example but if you always question
yourself that becomes your perspective
and that's how actually you cannot be
affected if a thing does change because you
if a thing does change because you
haven't been emotionally invested in it
and certainly you haven't invested like
a form of um what invested by ignorance
like oh I ignore this I'm not going to
question this because simply putting it
in question that ambiguity causes me
anxiety and that's why I will not
question it but that's completely the
opposite attitude of the attitude you
should have if you want to be free from
suffering
can give you an example well the example
would be why am I
practicing because I want to be free
from suffering am I free from
suffering so if the answer to
that is no yeah you know the answer you
know the answer am I fundamentally
ultimately Beyond suffering if the
answer is yes great you you already know
what you're doing but the answer is no
or I'm not sure I am means okay so all
these efforts I've been making yet I'm
still not free from suffering
perhaps I was
wrong not like that the Buddhist
teaching was wrong but perhaps I haven't
been doing it
rightly and again you might now because
you know all the investment of your
effort and and and emotionally charged
um practice that you've been doing for a
number of
years it it will make that person
uncomfortable if you start questioning
it like that it's going to make you
uncomfortable what if for this 20 years
of my meditation methods and techniques
and I'm not free from suffering
what if what if I've been doing it wrong
could I start again so the sooner you
start that questioning the less less of
an emotional investment it will become
if you've been doing it wrongly in other
words if you question it from the start
or if you start questioning it as soon
as you become aware of that you should
question it uh it's it's still a good
thing because it will prevent you from
periphera further if it were the wrong
way and
again if it were not the wrong way you
would have been free from suffering by
right
now so then you re-evaluate but not like
oh but what yeah I might have been wrong
but again what is my purpose to never be
wrong or to be free from
suffering to be free from suffering so
it doesn't matter even if 100 years I've
been wrong now I can be right then now I know
wrong now I can be right then now I know
that everything I've done is
wrong which means it's less likely that
I'll repeat the same mistakes cuz I
admitted it to my myself but if you
never question it never admit it you
will then blindly just go and keep
repeating the same thing did you deep
down inside no it doesn't work cuz it
hasn't free you from suffering after all
this time and even auna said himself if
you don't become a sodon in the first 5
years of practice you're not doing it
right if you don't get the right view
within the first 5 years of becoming a
monk commited to you're not doing it
right and that's quite accurate you're
not doing it right and you should really
like reevaluate quickly because the more
you invest in the wrong effort the
harder it will be to undo it CU more
conceit gets involved more sense of self
and also like more of that like oh I'm
I'm not going to look at
this because it's becoming the more you
ignore it the more unpleasant it will be
to face it later on